Guide to the Ulysses Kay papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Ulysses Kay Papers,
circa 1938-1995
Kay, Ulysses, 1917-1995.
37.29 linear feet (25 document boxes, 9 record storage cartons, 38 flat boxes, 42 CMI boxes, 2 card files, and 4 phonograph record boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1506
7341105
Ulysses Kay (1917-1995) was a noted twentieth-century American composer. The collection includes audio reels, biographical materials, correspondence, diaries, phonograph records, photographs, programs, and scores.
Biographical Note
Ulysses Kay (1917-1995) wrote more than 140 compositions in a wide range of forms – five operas, over 20 large orchestral works, more than 30 choral compositions, 15 chamber works, a ballet, and numerous other compositions for voice, solo instruments, film, and television.
Born in Tucson, Arizona, to a musical family, his mother encouraged him, and with the advice of her brother, Joe "King" Oliver, Kay studied piano, violin and saxophone. He entered the University of Arizona in 1934, receiving the Bachelor of Music in 1938. For the next two years he studied composition at the Eastman School of Music, University of Rochester, with Bernard Rogers and Howard Hanson, and received the Masters in Music in 1940. From 1941 to 1942 he studied with Paul Hindemith at Tanglewood and at Yale.
During World War II, Kay served in the U. S. Navy, playing with and arranging for the Navy Band, stationed at Quonset Point, Rhode Island. His most prominent composition from this period is "Of New Horizons" for concert band. Commissioned by Thor Johnson and performed by the New York Philharmonic, its premier took place in Lewisohn Stadium in July 1944.
Upon discharge from the Navy, he was awarded the Alice M. Ditson Fellowship for creative work at Columbia University, where he studied with Otto Luening from 1946 to 1947. During the summers, he was a resident at the Yaddo Festival in Saratoga Springs, New York. Major works from this period include: "Danse Calinda Suite," his ballet "The Rope," "Concerto for Orchestra," and the film music for "The Quiet One."
Many honors and scholarships followed, including a Fulbright Scholarship, and grants from the National Institute of Arts and Letters, and a Julius Rosenwald Fellowship. From 1949 to 1952, Kay received two "Prix de Rome" awards that allowed him to travel and study in Italy. The first African-American to receive the prize, it gave him residence in the American Academy in Rome, along with his new bride, Barbara Harrison of Chicago, whom he had married on August 20, 1949. Compositions from this period include: a Piano Quintet, a String Quartet, a Brass Quartet, "Sinfonia in E," and "Song of Ahab."
Returning to New York, Barbara taught music in Manhattan, and Ulysses accepted a position with Broadcast Music, Inc. (BMI) that would last from 1953 until 1968. Turning down several teaching positions, he preferred a job that gave him a regular schedule, allowing him to compose as much as possible. Compositions include: "A Lincoln Letter," "Six Dances for String Orchestra," "Fantasy Variations for Orchestra," and two operas, "The Boor," and "The Juggler of Our Lady."
In 1958, Kay was chosen to be a member of the first delegation of composers to the Soviet Union, a part of the U.S. State Department’s Cultural, Educational and Technical Exchange Agreement. The others in his group were Roy Harris, Peter Mennin, and Roger Sessions. During the month-long trip, Kay appreciated the interest in Jazz expressed by Russian composers and he played them recordings of the music of Miles Davis, Duke Ellington, Thelonious Monk, and Louis Armstrong, among others. He also attended performances of his own compositions, those of his fellow delegates, and the works of Russian composers. Upon his return, Hi-Fi Review published his account of the trip entitled "Thirty Days in Musical Russia."
Over the decade from 1958 to 1968, Kay received a large number of commissions, writing a total of 41 compositions, including: "New York: City of Magic," "Phoebus, Arise," "Forever Free," "Markings," "Aulos," and "Choral Triptych."
Barbara Kay was no less busy during these years. She participated in the Mississippi Freedom Rides during the summer of 1961. Arrested in Jackson, she was held in the Parchman Penitentiary for 41 days, after receiving a six-month sentence for disturbing the peace. William Faulkner once called the plantation prison "Destination Doom." Returning home, she participated in the first sit-in in the North, when Englewood residents took over city hall to protest racial segregation in the schools in 1962. During the boycott of the Englewood, New Jersey schools, she held a Freedom School in the basement of the Kay home. In 1966, she joined James Meredith’s "March Against Fear" in Mississippi. Later she continued to be active in the New Jersey chapter of the Congress of Racial Equality.
In 1968, at the age of 51, Kay left BMI to join the faculty of Herbert H. Lehman College as Professor of Music, teaching theory and composition, where he would serve until his retirement in 1988. During his 20 years of teaching, he produced three more operas, "The Capitoline Venus," "Jubilee," and "Frederick Douglass." Other works from this period include: "Theater Set," "Five Portraits," "Scherzi Musicali," "Western "Paradise," "Jersey Hours," "Tromba," "Once There Was a Man," "Chariots," "Festival Psalms," and "Visions" written to commemorate the 80th anniversary of William Grant Still’s birth.
As stated by Constance Tibbs Hobson and Deborra A. Richardson in their indispensable Ulysses Kay: A Bio-Bibliography (1994): "Kay’s contribution to America’s cultural life and to its contemporary music scene is outstanding. His distinguished career, reflecting personal industry, discipline, and will, sets an encouraging, honorable, and inspiring example for all who follow. His message to aspiring composers strongly advocates continued study and growth in order to better express one’s vision and individuality."
Scope and Content
Ulysses Kay (1917-1995) was a noted twentieth-century American composer. Kay’s papers include audio reels, biographical materials, correspondence, diaries, phonograph records, photographs, scores, and programs.
The strength of the papers is in their documentation of Kay’s work as a composer. Kay kept diaries to document his compositions, and these include information regarding the time of their composition, instrumentation, length, commissions, and performances. The papers also contain not only completed and published scores and libretti but also corrections, sketches, holographs, outlines, and information on source materials used for texts in his compositions. In addition, the papers include clippings, correspondence, photographs, programs, promotional material, and reviews that document the creation and performance of many of Kay’s works.
There is also some documentation of Kay’s work as a professor at Lehman College (1968-1989) in the papers, including appointment information, correspondence, press releases, and information on the Tribute Concert given at the time of his retirement in 1989. But while these records document some of Kay’s administrative and professional activities, there are few records that document his teaching activities at the College.
The papers also include audiovisual materials. The collection includes a wide range of audio materials; including reels, cassette tapes, commercially issued phonograph records, and acetate disks. The majority of this material consists of performances of Kay’s works, but there are also interviews, talks, and music used in television and commercials. There is very little video in the collection. There is also good coverage of Kay’s professional career in the photographs contained in the collection. While the collection does not contain a large volume of photographs, many of the professional photographs in the collection are both identified and dated, and document a period of several decades.
The papers include some documentation of Kay’s family and personal life, but it is not extensive. Materials include family photographs and correspondence, personal correspondence, and condolence letters written to the family upon Kay’s death in 1995. There is also a small amount of material that was kept by Barbara Kay including correspondence, photographs, and materials related to the Civil Rights movement.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in eleven series and several subseries.
Series I: Kay’s Diaries, 1949-1991
Series II: Music by Kay, 1939-1991
Series III: Performance Programs, 1938-1994
Subseries III.1: Programs Featuring Kay, 1938-1994
Subseries III.2: Programs Featuring Others, 1946-1989
Series IV: Biographical Files, 1940s-1995
Series V: Correspondence, 1941-1995
Subseries V.1: General Correspondence, 1953-1995
Subseries V.2: Family Correspondence, circa 1944-1994
Subseries V.3: Personal Correspondence, 1953-1980, 1991-1994
Subseries V.4: Professional Correspondence, 1941-1994
Series VI: Professional Subject Files, 1941-1997
Series VII: Season Files and Other Clippings, 1941-1998
Subseries VII.1: Season Files, 1941-1989
Subseries VII.2: Other Clippings, 1949-1998
Series VIII: Photographs, 1920s-1993, undated
Subseries VIII.1: Professional Photographs of Kay, 1940-1991, undated
Subseries VIII.2: Other Professional Photographs, circa 1940s-1993
Subseries VIII.3: Family and Personal Photographs, 1920s-1990
Series IX: Audiovisual Materials, 1947-1988, undated
Subseries IX.1: Audio Recordings, 1947-1988, undated
Subseries IX.2: Video, 1959, undated
Series X: Barbara Kay Files, circa 1955-1991
Series XI. Annotated, Inscribed, and Signed Materials, circa 1947-1986
Subseries XI.1: Recordings, 1958, 1984-1986
Subseries XI.2: Scores, circa 1947-1972
Subseries XI.3: Books, circa 1953-1983
Subjects
Cohn, Arthur, 1910-1998; Dorr, Donald--Correspondence; Dorr, Donald--Librettos; Kay, Ulysses, 1917-1995; Melnechuck, Theodore--Correspondence; Rochberg, George--Correspondence; Herbert H. Lehman College--Music Department; Herbert H. Lehman College--faculty; African American Composers; College Teachers; Composers--United States--20th century; Composition (Music)--20th century; Musicians; Music--United States--20th century; Television Music--Scores; Universities and colleges--faculty; Audiotapes; Clippings; Programs (Documents); Correspondence; Diaries; Librettos; Operas; Photographs; Scores
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
This collection has no restrictions. If you would like to use audiovisual materials in Series IX, please contact the library to discuss access options as most of these materials have not been reformatted and are not readily available for use.
Acquisition
Gift and purchase from Virginia, Hillary, and Melinda Kay, 2009
Finding aid is available online.
- Series I: Kay's Diaries, 1949-1991
  This series contains Kay's two diaries. The main focus of the diaries is a list of compositions, with information regarding instrumentation, work length, dedications, commissions, composition dates, premiere performances, etc. The first diary also includes information about Kay's reproduction costs, his honors, and his travels. The second diary continues his list of travels, beginning at the back of the volume, and includes composition information about his opera Frederick Douglass near the beginning of the volume.
  - Diaries, 1949-1990, 1976-1991, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 1 to 2)
- Series II: Music by Kay, 1939-1991
  This series contains documents pertaining to original works and one arrangement by Kay, in addition to a short song composed by his daughter. The main focus of the series is Kay's sketches, holographs, and published scores; however, other pertinent documents, such as libretti, correspondence, and notes have also been included in the series. The coverage of the records is quite comprehensive, but some works listed in Kay's diaries and in Hobson's and Richardson's bibliography remain unrepresented in the collection, and it lacks a few fully-realized scores. The compositions missing materials include: Christmas Carol (1943); Concerto for Orchestra (1948); Suite from "The Quiet One" (1948); Partita in A (1950); Phoebus, Arise (1958-1959); Two Pieces for Orchestra (1964); Four Hymn-Anthems (1965); Aulos (1967); Jubilee (1974-1976); a cadenza to one of Mozart's piano concerti (1979); and Everett Suite (1988).
  The series is arranged chronologically by the compositions' years of completion, following the order outlined in Kay's diaries wherever possible. Within each work, materials are arranged in approximate chronological order, but for works using texts or libretti, these are listed first. Unidentified sketches and notes appear at the end of the series.
  There is additional information regarding Kay's compositions and activities in Series VI: Professional Subject Files.
  - Sinfonietta for Orchestra, 1939
    - Holograph, circa 1939-1952 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Full scores, 1952 (2 items) (Box 5, Folder 2)
      (facsimile)
  - Sonatine for Viola and Piano, 1939
    - Holograph, circa 1939-1946 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Viola part, circa 1939-1946 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      (facsimile; contains markings)
    - Score, circa 1939-1946 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Four Poems, 1939
    - Score, circa 1939 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Concerto for Oboe and Orchestra, 1940
    - Holograph of full score, circa 1940-1949 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Full score, circa 1940-1949 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Full score, circa 1940-1949 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Piano reduction, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Piano reduction, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Five Mosaics, 1940
    - Holograph, circa 1940-1952 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Score, circa 1940-1952 (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Sonata for Piano, 1940
    - Holograph, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Score, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Thirteen Pieces for Children, 1940
    (revised as Ten Short Essays, 1957)
    - Holograph of No. 2 "Tender Thoughts", circa 1940 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      (contains additional markings)
    - Score for No. 7 "Two Voices", circa 1940 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Score, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Danse Calinda,1940
    (see also Suite from the Ballet "Danse Calinda", 1947)
    - Holograph of piano reduction for Scene 1, circa 1940-1952 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Synopsis and note, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Four Pieces for Male Chorus, 1941
    - Choir score, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Choir score, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      (facsimile; final two pages reversed)
    - Piano reduction, circa 1941 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Score for No. 4 "Spanish Johnny", 1948 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Two Songs, 1941
    - Score, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Score, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Sonata for Bassoon and Piano, 1941
    - Holograph, circa 1941-1952 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Three Pieces for 2 Horns and 2 Trombones, 1941
    (also called Three Pieces for Horns and Trombones)
    - Holograph set of parts, circa 1941 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Full score, circa 1941-1952 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Full score, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Sonatina for Violin and Piano, 1942
    - Score, circa 1942-1946 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Score, circa 1942-1946 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Score with separate violin part, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Sonatina for 2 Violins, 1942
    - Holograph, circa 1942-1952 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Score, circa 1942-1952 (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - Three Fanfares for Four Trumpets, 1942
    - Holographs of parts, circa 1942 (Box 24, Folder 13)
      (contained within full sketch of Scherzi Musicali (1968), on the versos of pages 1-4)
    - Set of parts, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 24)
      (incomplete: missing part for Trumpet IV; contains markings)
    - Score with set of parts, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Little Suite for String Quartet, 1942
    - Holograph of full score, circa 1942-1946 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Holographs of parts, circa 1942-1946 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Full score, 1946 (Box 38, Folder 3)
    - Set of parts, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Sonata for Viola and Piano, 1942
    - Holographs of viola and piano parts, circa 1942-1952 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - As Joseph Was A-Walking, 1943
    - Choir score of three-part version, circa 1943 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Choir score of three part version, circa 1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      (facsimile; contains markings, including sketch of fourth part)
    - Holograph of four-part version, circa 1955 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Submission score of four-part version with correspondence, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      (correspondence from Don H. Razey at Carl Fischer, Inc.)
  - Untitled, 1943
    (three songs to texts by Sara Teasdale)
    - Holograph, circa 1943 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Flute Quintet, 1943
    - Holograph of full score, circa 1943-1952 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Holographs of parts, circa 1943-1952 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Prelude for Unaccompanied Flute, 1943
    (revised and recopied 1957)
    - Holograph, undated (Box 6, Folder 34)
      (incomplete)
    - Scores, 1976 (2 items) (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Suite in B, 1943
    - Holograph of piano part, circa 1943-1952 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Holograph of oboe part, circa 1943-1952 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Suite for Brass Choir, 1943
    - Holograph of full score, circa 1943-1952 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Holographs of parts, circa 1943-1952 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Full score, circa 1943-1952 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Full score, circa 1943-1952 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Sets of parts, circa 1943-1952 (2 items) (Box 7, Folder 7)
      (facsimile; contain markings)
  - Duo for Flute and Oboe, 1943
    (also called Suite for Flute and Oboe)
    - Holograph, circa 1943-1952 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Holograph, circa 1953 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Scores, 1964 (2 items) (Box 7, Folder 10)
      (one contains markings)
  - Little Suite for C Recorder and Piano, 1943
    - Holograph of piano part, circa 1943-1952 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Holograph of recorder part, circa 1943-1952 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Holograph of recorder part transposed for b-flat clarinet, circa 1943-1952 (Box 7, Folder 13)
      (found with score in Folder 14)
    - Score with separate recorder part, circa 1943-1952 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - A Cradle Hymn, 1943
    - Choir score, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Choir score, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      (facsimile; label pasted over Kay's name; contains markings)
  - Prelude and Air, 1943
    - Holograph of piano part, circa 1943-1952 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Holograph of tuba part, circa 1943-1952 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Serenade, 1943
    - Holograph of piano part, circa 1943-1952 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Holograph of tuba part, circa 1943-1952 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Lift Every Voice and Sing, 1943
    - Holograph, circa 1943-1952 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Come Away, Come Away Death, 1944
    - Full sketch, circa 1944 (Box 7, Folder 20)
      (in ink; contains further markings in pencil)
    - Holograph, circa 1944-1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Choir score, circa 1944-1952 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Choir scores, 1954 (2 items) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Evocation, 1944
    (two versions: for concert band and for orchestra)
    - Holograph of version for concert band, circa 1944-1952 (Box 41)
      (includes holographs of clarinet parts)
    - Holographs of clarinet parts from version for concert band, circa 1944-1952 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Full score of version for concert band, circa 1944-1952 (Box 42)
    - Full score of version for concert band, circa 1944-1952 (Box 43)
    - Holograph of version for orchestra, circa 1944-1952 (Box 38, Folder 4)
    - Full score of version for orchestra, circa 1944-1952 (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - Of New Horizons, 1944
    - Full score, circa 1944 (Box 44)
    - Negatives for pages from full score, circa 1953 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      (includes negatives for pages 39 and 40)
    - Full score, circa 1953 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Miniature scores, 1961 (2 items) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Sinfonia Selection, 1944
    - Holograph, circa 1944 (Box 39, Folder 5)
  - Suite for Orchestra, 1945
    - Full score, circa 1945 (Box 7, Folder 23)
      (facsimile; label covering Kay's name; contains markings)
    - Miniature score, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      (contains markings)
    - Miniature score, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Miniature scores, 1948 (2 items) (Box 1, Folder 18)
      (different editions)
  - Allegro for Oboe and String Orchestra, 1946
    - Holograph, circa 1946 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      (includes alternate final page)
    - Full score, circa 1946 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Brief Elegy, circa 1946-1952
    - Copies of full score, circa 1952 (2 items) (Box 8, Folder 3)
      (facsimile; original score contained markings)
    - Piano reductions with separate oboe parts, 1964 (2 items) (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Dedication, 1946
    - Holograph of choir score, circa 1946-1953 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Holograph of piano reduction, circa 1946-1953 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Choir scores, circa 1946-1953 (4 items) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Eight Inventions, 1946
    (revised as Four Inventions, 1946)
    - Holograph with note, circa 1946-1952 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Score, circa 1946-1952 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Four Inventions, 1946
    (revision of Eight Inventions, 1946)
    - Holograph, circa 1946-1953 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - The Rope: a design for dance, 1946
    (revised and retitled as Ancient Saga: a design for modern dance, 1947)
    - Holograph, circa 1946-1952 (Box 8, Folder 9)
      (contains additional markings in pencil)
    - Score, circa 1946-1952 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - A Short Overture, 1946
    - Full score, circa 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 11)
      (facsimile; all traces of Kay's identity hidden with tape; contains markings)
    - Negatives for parts, circa 1953 (Box 8, Folder 12)
      (date from envelope: relevant portion included)
    - Full score, circa 1953 (Box 45)
      (same edition as negatives; contains markings)
    - Miniature scores, 1973 (2 items) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Ancient Saga: a design for modern dance, 1947
    (revision of The Rope, 1946)
    - Full score, undated (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Full score, undated (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Suite from the Ballet "Danse Calinda", 1947
    (see also Danse Calinda, 1940)
    - Holograph of piano reduction for Scene 2, circa 1947-1953 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Score of piano reduction for Scene 2, circa 1947-1953 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Score of piano reduction for Scene 2, circa 1947-1953 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Song of Jeremiah, 1945-1947
    (three versions: original version for baritone, women's chorus, and organ (1945); first revision for baritone, women's chorus, and orchestra (1947); final version for baritone, mixed chorus, and orchestra (1947))
    - Sketches and notes, circa 1945-1947 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      (includes correspondence from "Bil," undated)
    - Holograph of original version, circa 1945-1952 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Full score of original version, circa 1945-1952 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Pages from draft holograph of first revision, circa 1945-1947 (6 items) (Box 9, Folder 4)
      (in ink with additional markings)
    - Full score of first revised version, circa 1947 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Full score of first revised version, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Full score of first revised version, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 7)
      (facsimile; contains markings, including revisions and sketches for mixed chorus)
    - Holographs of orchestral parts for final version, circa 1947-1952 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      (incomplete set: includes holographs for woodwind and brass parts only)
    - Holograph of vocal score for final version, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Holograph of piano reduction for final version, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Suite for Strings, 1947
    (originally Songs for Strings)
    - Full score, undated (Box 8, Folder 15)